OK, let's get started.
Artet wir sind gut online, ok.
OK, I see that we're losing some people even though this is a Thursday.
Let's see when we will hit the bottom.
Hopefully, hopefully not 0.
But you have all the lectures online so you don't.
We don't require attendance over here.
The the the best way you can learn is the most important for me.
As long as you learn and get the basic concepts and principles, OK, today we're going to cover
something that's really important for your labs.
Also, it's really important for thinking in parallel, I would say, because we're going to look at
describing hardware using human design languages.
And we're going to specifically look at a particular language called Verilogue, but essentially all
hardware description language that are fundamentally similar.
And we're going to look at some design principles to enable this hardware, especially hierarchical
design, top down and bottom up design, and different ways of representing hardware.
Some of them will be very low level, some of them will be much higher level.
And both ways are important to know for the reasons that we will discuss.
Some of these may be automated in the future, but if you don't know, you don't, you may not actually
figure out how the automated things are actually doing in terms of performance, efficiency,
etcetera.
So it's always good to know what's going on underneath, even if AI eventually takes over and does
some of these for you in the future.
And I believe this is actually a part that is more amenable to that.
And if you know what you're doing or how the how the how the underlying hardware description is made
and also is optimised or can be optimised, then you can do much better in, in, in navigating how
the AI optimise it.
So it's good to think about these things.
I have a picture that I'm going to show related to this later on also.
OK, But before we jump into it, this is what we covered in the last few lectures.
We essentially are done with combinational logic.
You should know essentially everything on this slide.
We actually looked at a lot of combinational logic blocks, which is part of the combinational logic
lecture.
We talked about logical completeness.
It was your task to prove NAND and NOR is logically complete.
Basically can represent any Boolean equation using only Nands and also build anything using only
NAND gates, which is a fascinating result I think.
And we covered sequential logic in the last lecture.
We talked about how to store information, how to design sequential logic circuits, and how to build
finite state machines.
And essentially we said that everything in a computer is a finite state machine.
A computer is a collection of finite state machines.
It may have many states, millions or billion states, but it's still a finite state machine.
And we're going to design some of these finite state machines at the end of this lecture using
Verilog.
Sounds good.
OK, OK, this is the agenda for today.
We're going to talk about HDL or hardware description languages, and then first we're going to
implement combinational logic with it.
And then we're going to implement sequential logic and finite state machines.
The Verilog slides are part of a tutorial also.
We may not cover everything in detail, but it's good for you to study them on your own if we don't
cover every single part of it.
And they'll be definitely very beneficial for your labs.
In fact, in the lab lectures this week, you may design A finite state machine.
I don't know if you will go over the Verilog depend, depends on your questions also, but it could be
useful for you to think about it.
Or at least next week also, OK, soon we will use these components to design a full microprocessor.
So next week, the week after we're going to design microprocessor.
So everything will build on top of what we will learn.
And in the labs, you're going to design A microprocessor using information that we have gathered in
the last few lectures, plus today's lecture.
So real programming will start with today's lecture.
OK, this is the data path.
So I'm going to leave that here.
These are the readings for this week.
Again, if you understand everything, you don't need to read anything.
But reading is always good for reinforcing concepts.
And H&H Harris and Harris as the nice description of hardware description languages and Verilog.
And tomorrow we're going to cover timing and verification.
Sounds good.
OK.
But before we jump into today's lecture, somebody may be questioning what's the point of this
lecture?
Maybe I'll ask you the question.
Who painted this painting?
Anybody knows?
Nobody.
Anybody can.
Yes, maybe AI.
Maybe AI.
OK, that's a good guess.
But no, there's a real painting painted by a real human.
I don't remember the name of the artist who was living in Belgium and he was painting happiness.
OK, I see my grade wrong but good guess.
It's good to try, it's hard to guess.
Do you know why?
It's hard to guess because it's not an extremely impressive painting.
It's not something that someone would be remembered by.
Do you guys agree or no?
OK, maybe you just say agree.
Fine.
But I think a lot of art critics would agree.
Not that I'm an art critic, but that's the case.
If I told you that this guy did it, can you name this guy?
There you go.
Salvador Dali But you won't remember Salvador Dali by this Salvador Dali.
Well, maybe I'll ask you who painted this one.
Dali OK, there you go.
Everybody remember Salvador Dali by this thing, right?
The burning giraffe or giraffes.
Anyway, I'm not going to interpret this painting.
But this was also Dali who painted this painting.
This is the same person and they all have implications of this painting you can go and find which
may be fitting for today, what's going on in the world.
My point is this, we're covering these lectures because if you want to be like Dali, you may or may
not want to be, depending on what you want to do.
You got to learn the basic principles before you can use them, ignore them, or consciously choose it
to even break them.
If you don't know the principles, then you're basically shooting in the dark.
The AI is doing programming for you, and you have no idea when it does something wrong, and you have
no idea when it does something useless, and you have no idea when it does something inefficient,
right?
You're basically shooting in the dark.
You're relying on someone else's expertise.
That's why we're covering this.
That's why you're covering a lot of these basics that may be eventually automated by AI.
Who knows?
We don't know for sure.
Does that make sense?
So remember these pictures if you ever doubt or if someone ever challenges something saying that why
are you learning these things?
Why are you learning these basic things that people are not going to deal with 100 years from now?
It's good to think about that.
OK, I like Dali.
OK, so let's jump into hardware description languages.
So this is a modern microprocessor.
Not as modern.
It's 10 years old.
As you can see, it had 1.75 billion transistors.
We're going to see a lot of the things that go into this jargon over here later.
It's one of the state-of-the-art process of its of its time.
This was 22,021 sixteen billion transistors.
So you can see that the number multiplied by ten in four years or so.
Different companies, but good to think about.
This is the next generation of that M1 put together using two chips bonded together using some
interconnects.
That's 114 billion.
And we've already seen pictures like this where you have 1.2 trillion transistors on a wafer and 2.6
trillion.
And this is something what someone is holding.
Basically, we have, we can put a lot of things on a chip, right?
Transistors are the basic building blocks, but there's some complexity that's associated with it.
And this is something from Wikipedia.
If you look at memory, memory is even worse.
Basically, memory chips have orders of magnitude more transistors and computation chips, and these
are some example chips.
You can see that my numbers earlier for GPUs was actually out outdated.
The number over here is 208 billion, apparently on NVIDIA B100.
Assuming you trust who whoever changed Wikipedia over here.
But they're not that bad, at least in these things.
OK, so it's good to think about this basically, basically this pose A complexity challenge.
How do you actually deal with this complexity?
How do you actually put things together on a chip?
Design things.
And this is where languages that are specialized for describing hardware come into play.
Essentially what we need for hardware design is the ability to describe and specify designs and then
increasing the complex designs and also to simulate their behaviour.
And you're going to do both of them in the labs actually.
And we're going to talk about functional simulation as well as timing simulation timing tomorrow.
And also you would like to be able to synthesize this hardware, meaning automatically designed
portions of it.
You describe the hardware and someone needs to map it to the underlying logic gates for example, or
transistors or technologies.
And that part is usually done through electronic design automation tools.
Today.
This is the subject of another lecture if you really want to understand how they operate.
Not this lecture, but for all of these you start with describing the hardware, right?
So you need to have an error free path to implementation eventually.
And hardware description language actually enable all of the above.
It enables description.
Even though they're called description, they also enable simulation and also a synthesis of the
hardware.
So these are languages designed to describe hardware.
Based on what?
Based on the name.
Based on what the name suggests, and there are similarly featured HDLS, one of the most popular
ones, Verilog, and you're going to use that.
There are versions of Verilog, Verilog, System Verilog, etcetera.
The principles are basically the same.
Syntax is different.
Some things are easier, some things are harder in one version versus the other, but I'm going to
give you the basic principles in the end.
We're going to talk a little bit about syntax also because syntax is always interesting but annoying
also sometimes this is where actually AI can help a lot.
So if you learn one language, it's not hard to learn another in this particular case, right?
And mapping between language is usually mechanical, especially for the commonly used subset of the
languages.
So this is a boring slide.
A little bit of history.
There are two major languages.
One is Verilog and the other is VHDL.
Surprisingly, they were developed very late, meaning 1980s.
That's relatively late in the development of computing and they became standards relatively quickly.
We will use Verilog in this course, but other people may use VHDL, and again, you can easily see the
similarities and differences between them.
So why do we have specialised languages for hardware?
Well, my answer is hardware is special.
It's special because you do some special things in hardware, as we will see, right?
As we have seen also right, First, they enable easy description of hardware structures which may not
exist in a higher level programming language that you may be used to Python, for example.
In a Python, how do you describe a flip flop?
How do you describe concurrent assignment of different things to a stateful thing?
It's good to think about that.
And also a high a hardware description language enables seamless expression of parallelism inherent
in hardware.
So for example, this hardware description language usually has specialised keywords to describe
wires, gates, registers, flip flops, clock, rising and falling edge.
We're going to see that.
Hopefully you remember the clock and rising and fall edge.
These are concepts that are necessary to actually build sequential logic, right?
Essentially combinational and sequential logic elements.
And for the second one, all hardware logic updates concurrently.
Basically you actually you, you design something and there's a lot of concurrency in hardware.
The way you synchronize to different concurrent operations is through clock, assuming you're doing
synchronous design.
If you don't have synchronous design, it's much harder to synchronize things.
So we're going to see that concurrent operations specified in the hardware description language and
having both of these above is a specification, simulation and synthesis.
It enables the hardware designer to design something better.
It enables the tools to simulate things better, and it enables the electronic design automation
tools to map what's described to the underlying library.
Let's say, let's say a library of logic gates, much better.
People have tried, for example, to use high level languages to describe hardware.
You take C or Java or Python or whatever pick pick your favorite language and you try to map it to
the hardware and people have not been successful in that so far.
Even though you may be able to actually describe the hardware and also implement it, the resulting
hardware is very inefficient, either very slow or very expensive or power hungry or all of the
above, usually all of the above in the end.
So it's it's very hard to get from a very general purpose language that's designed to write software
to a hardware implementation versus having a special language for hardware and get to a hardware
implementation compared to that.
OK, Hopefully you'll see some of these as we go through this lecture.
So let's do some hardware design using HDL.
So how do you actually do this design?
You have 1 trillion transistors and you want to use them for something.
We're going to see a lot of principles for designing processors.
Later on, you may decide to use some of those principles and you eventually decide there will be
some modules that you want.
This is some example over here, right?
You have some cores.
We're going to delve a lot into these cores.
You have some caches.
We're going to see more of that how how they are constructed.
Memory controllers, we're going to see some of that also and memory.
And essentially, you have these different modules, right?
And in the end, if you want to tame complexity, you have to separate things into modules.
That's the divide and conquer approach, right?
You separate things into modules, have a hierarchy of them.
For example, a cache block that has a lot of memory over here has smaller modules internally.
And it's a hierarchy of modules where I'm going to give you some examples.
Essentially you start with predefined primitive gates.
For example, these are the smallest modules that you may have, and then you build simple modules on
top of them.
By instantiating these gates for example components like multiplexers, decoders like we have done in
lecture, right?
And you, you build more complex modules like like an ALU arithmetic logic unit like we have done,
right?
It consists of multiplexers, adders, wires, gates, etcetera.
And we do this by instantiating simpler modules.
And having this hierarchy clearly helps with the complex design, complexity of the design.
This is similar to having like functions and methods in programming, right?
You program using functions or methods.
And these help you build a hierarchy of functions or a call stack of functions, which could be
useful in really programming as opposed to writing everything as a sequential code.
And there are no functions, no methods.
It's very hard to read also, right?
OK, so basically complexity is a big issue in microprocessors today.
Even though software is complex, hardware is actually very complex too, because usually the
understanding is that hardware should work.
That understanding doesn't translate easily to software.
Actually, it's unfortunate that if you think about it, software is a more iterative process.
The first version may not work.
I suggest enabling your first version to work very well, but the first version may not work and you
can keep iterating, change the software because soft, right?
Whereas with hardware, if the first version doesn't work, you manufactured it, you're going to
manufacture it again, right?
It's very expensive to do this.
That's why first version should ideally work.
So if you don't actually do the right thing when you're designing, you may actually get not working
hardware.
And if with complex hardware, it's very easy to get something that doesn't work.
OK, So OK, basically what is the size of a module also becomes a question what what do you
synthesise to gates?
This is actually a real question that people are trying to answer.
I'm not going to answer that.
So there are usually two types of design methodologies.
1 is top down, the other is bottom up.
People usually use both when they're designing complex systems.
So top down is essentially you define a top level module, let's say microprocessor, and identify the
sub modules necessary to build the top level module.
You have a bunch of sub modules.
You may have, for example, an instruction fetch engine and then instruction decode engine and then
an instruction execution engine and then memory access engine and then instruction finishing
engine.
We're going to see that actually in several lectures.
And these may be different modules that are put together in some way and then clearly they consist
of other sub modules and eventually you come to leaf cells.
Leaf cells are circuit components that cannot be further divided.
Based on what you're doing, they could be logic gates, they could be primitive cell library elements
that can be synthesised that may map to different libraries.
So essentially it could be an adder for example, but it could be an AND gate also, right?
It depends, but hopefully you get the idea right.
This is the modular design that you have or you can do bottom up design.
You first identify what building blocks that are available to you.
Leaf cells.
Someone may provide this to you.
Basically, someone may say you're going to use only these blocks because these are the blocks that I
can efficiently manufacture in my factory, right Fabrication technology and I'm and you should
design your microprocessor using these blocks.
This is what happens when people manufacture, for example, their microprocessors and when, when they
send it to TSMC, for example, they manufacture in Taiwan or somewhere.
You get some libraries and you're, you're supposed to work with them.
And then you build bigger modules using these blocks and eventually you have a top level module.
So these two methodologies are bottom up, top down.
Usually it's a combination of both.
And sometimes you may say, oh, I want another leaf module, please add it to your library.
And if the manufacturer is nice and if you give them enough money, they may be able to do that.
You know, so top down is good because you can request things.
Bottom up is good because maybe you're poor and you cannot pay a lot and you basically deal with the
leaf cells over there.
Sounds good.
OK, so hopefully you understand the trade-offs, which is not which which comes up actually in
software design as well.
OK, so let's talk about this module.
You can define modules in Verilog.
It's the main building block in Verilog.
Essentially you define the name of the module.
In this case, it's example.
You need to define the directions of its ports.
There are some inputs and outputs.
This is a hardware block.
Basically.
Now we're defining a hardware block and you need to name the ports ABC and Y here.
And then you need to describe the functionality of the module using programming using the syntax of
Verilog.
So let's take a look at one module over here.
This is a module definition, example module ABCY.
Inputs our ABC output is Y and then you describe the circuit and you do end module.
Again this is syntax boring automated easily.
But this is at your module.
I've already said all of these, so and you need to declare the type of these ports, input and
output.
So again, syntax, these two descriptions are functionally identical.
You can put the input declarations inside or you can actually merge them over here, depends on the
readability and coding standards, etcetera.
So you can combine the declaration and direction.
So if you have multi input and output, multi bit input and output is called a bus, a set of wires
essentially.
You have an array definition that looks like this.
Range end, range start and number of bits is range end minus range start plus one.
For example, this is a 32 bit bus named A, It's an input.
This is a 8, an 8 bit bus named B1, It's an output.
There's an 8 bit bus also named B2 and this is single wire, single bit bus essentially.
I think I already said this.
So normally you use like this.
It's preferred over this definition.
So it's good practice to be consistent.
Either you always use 31 zero or zero 31, but not both.
Otherwise you will confuse people.
Yes.
Is there a reason you specify a start index?
Start index like 0?
That's how it is.
I mean that's the syntax maybe.
Maybe you always want to connect it to the top bytes, let's say, right, Because there are 8 bits
over here.
And maybe this is semantically that B1 always goes to the top 8 bytes bits.
It could be, for example, the top 8 bits of a 16 bit number, and that's what you want to do.
So this may be the way.
I wouldn't name it B1 in that case.
It might be the significant byte of B or something like that.
You know, yes, a is 30, 232 bits, yes, 32 bits.
And then?
Which one?
It's the, it's the same notation, right?
It's 15 through 8, but it's, it basically says 8 bits, right?
There's also 8 bits.
It's just written that way.
OK, so how do you manipulate bits?
So these are easy things.
Again, you can slice the bits, you can concatenate the bits.
So slicing the bits looks like this.
For example, you have a 16 bit long bus, you have an 8 bit short bus.
And you can assign those 8 bits to be the bits 12 through 5 of the long bus, right?
You basically slice the middle bits over here.
It's possible to do it.
As you can see, that's, that's why you basically a 16 bit wire, get the middle 8 bits and assign it
to the short bus, right?
That's what we're doing over here.
And you should be able to do that in hardware clearly concatenation.
Basically, if you want to concatenate 4 different bits, let's say you have an, you have a bus called
A.
And if you want to create a four bit value that consists of the 0 TH bit of a, again 0 TH bit of a
copied and then the first bit of A and the second bit of a, you can concatenate like this.
Or you can duplicate things.
For example, if you want to duplicate the first bit of A, the 0 TH bit, I should, I should say 0 TH
bit, really 0 TH bit of A.
And if you want to duplicate it four times, this is one way of doing it.
X is essentially A4 bit value that duplicates the zero bit four times.
Or you could specify it this way.
These both specify the same thing, essentially multiple copies.
So it's good to think about these things.
And it's relatively easy, as you can see.
Yes.
So are these long bosses, short bosses, X&Y, are these inputs outputs that we define, or are they
new variables that we now declare?
Yeah, there are wires here.
You can see that they're declared as wires, but they could also be inputs, they could be outputs.
But in this case, you have a declaration called wire.
Wire that's not part of your module.
You'll see that it's going to be part of your module itself.
Inside.
It's not an input, it's not an output, but it's inside the module.
There's some wires, OK, And then assign statement is used when you want to assign some value to some
wire.
OK, yes.
And then the index.
So it it gets the value that's assigned to it.
So if it's an input, it needs to be supplied as input, right?
For example, a four bit value, if the value is 1111, A zero will be 1.
If the value is 1110, the a zero will be 0.
OK, OK, so there's some basic syntax.
The word log is case sensitive.
Fortunately or unfortunately these are the.
These are not the same things.
Basically you need to deal with case sensitivity.
Names cannot start with numbers.
That's what they decided to do.
White space are ignored and you can make comments that are single line comments and multi line
comments.
Hopefully these are easy to think about.
OK, let's talk about two main styles of HDL implementation because we're going to look at the lower
level style first, which is structural and then we're going to look at the higher level style which
is behavioural.
Structural is essentially gate level.
The module body contains gate level description of the circuit and you define describe how the
modules are interconnected each other and each model module contains other modules or instances and
you also specify the interconnection between these modules.
I'm going to give you examples of this soon.
Essentially you can describe the hierarchical modules that are defined as gates.
So it's very low level because you start with gates.
Behavioural on the other hand is very high level.
It's more similar to higher level programming language, although there will be differences that are
specialised elements as we will see.
The module body contains functional description of the circuit.
As opposed to using gates like and gates or gates, we're going to use a functional description.
If and else statement, for example will be one example or a for loop, we'll be able to do that.
It contains logical and mathematical operators like plus, minus, etcetera.
So the level of abstraction is higher than gate love.
Now this is useful in specifying complex things, but this also leads to many possible gate level
realisations from this behavioural description because the person who is describing it doesn't
really specify the gate level description.
OK, so there's a lot of open-ended potential compilation of this and there are many, many practical
designs actually use both.
You need to use a combination of both in the end, because structural is, you could potentially
design everything with structural gate level, very log, no question about that.
And that's a very good learning experience for someone who starts, but it's very tedious.
Essentially, it's not easy to design a trillion like billion gate processor with every gate
specified by the designer.
OK, so but we're going to start with structural because it's easier to understand and then gate
behaviour will follow.
So this is an example of module that I want to design.
Let's say it does something right.
It has a top level module.
It's inputs are a select and C, let's say.
And then it's output is Y, and it consists of two smaller modules that are identical to each other.
One of them looks like this, the other looks like this.
And they're connected using a wire called N1.
OK, so this is our schematic.
Usually when you design A module, it's good to do a pictorial schematic to do the design.
That's actually what in general people do.
And I've already said what what is said over here.
Now let's take a look at how you would instantiate it or how you would describe this module in
Verilog.
So you can see that there's a top module, there's some inputs and outputs and you also describe you
also define the wires that connect.
That's part of this top level module, as you can see, right?
And don't forget then module.
And then there's a small module.
You can see the inputs AB and output Y.
And then there's some description.
It does something.
Let's assume it doesn't matter what it does actually.
But because we're not, we're not going to deal with that.
We're really looking at how you combine modules over here.
So that's the top module over here.
These are the small modules.
And this is a wire.
You need to declare these.
Unfortunately, it doesn't automatically infer that it's a wire because we will see some other types
of things later on.
You can see that this is the first instantiation of the small module.
So the top level module has a small module.
I first instantiate it this way.
Here I'm the The instantiation describes that the A input of the module is connected to the A input
of A input of the first small module is connected to the A input of the top level module.
Right B input dot B specifies that B input of the first small module is connected as cell input of
the top level module and the Y output of the small module is connected to the wire N1.
OK, that's how you'd specify again it's syntax.
You're really describing how things are connected over here.
And this is the second instantiating the small one for the second time.
Here you're describing the.
A input of the second one is connected to the M1 wire that is which is the output of this one.
And B input is connected to the C input of the top level module.
And the Y output of this is connected to the Y output of the top level module, right?
That's what we've done basically.
Naming is important.
Clearly, if you don't want to deal with the naming, this is what you could do.
So instead of doing this dot A dot B dot Y, you basically follow the order aby over here, a cell and
one, for example.
Implicitly.
If you don't explicitly specify which input is connected to what, you basically fall back on the
order.
It's possible to do it, but pin order is very important.
This is a safer choice, clearly, because here you can basically order these in any way.
I wouldn't recommend that still, but it's harder to make a mistake because you're explicitly
specifying which input is connected to the which thing at the higher level module, right?
But you could do either way.
OK, so a short form is not good practice in general as it reduces code maintainability.
OK, so now let's build a multiplexer.
You know multiplexers.
This is our beautiful 2 to 1 multiplexer from previous lecture and the last lecture.
From the previous lecture and the previous to previous lecture.
Actually, we've seen this multiple times.
So Verilog actually supports multiple ways of building a multiplexer.
Let's take a look at how to use logic gates.
Actually, Verilog has basic logic gates as its primitives.
These primitives are instantiated like modules, except that they're predefined in Verilog and do not
need a module definition.
For example, you don't need to define an and module because and is a special thing in Verilog.
So this is our multiplexer 2 input multiplexer.
You have two inputs D0D1.
You can see that I you can omit inputs if you if you actually use the input over here, another input
S select input and an output Y.
And if you want to do a structural description, you need to declare the wires Y1Y2 and then not
select, which is actually shown over here as a bubble.
And this is the gate double description.
You first invert select.
The output is not select.
This is our G1 over here, which is the bubble actually.
And then you have an Ant which takes the not select which is here and then D0AS inputs and then
outputs Y1 which is this one that's G2 and gate over here.
And then you have another Ant, which is this one G3 which takes S and D1 as inputs and outputs Y2,
which is our wire which we declared.
And then you you describe the OR gates which takes Y1 and Y2AS inputs and outputs Y, which is
connected to the output of the Max 2 module.
It's an OR gate, did I say?
And it's an OR gate.
OK, basically this is our Multiplex here that we knew from before, right?
Looks nice.
And we exactly described it in hardware using the primitives that Verilog provides.
And it could keep doing this.
You could do this all with Nans.
It's fun, but it gets very boring and tiring after some point because you know you can't do it.
So you need to raise the level of abstraction, right?
Abstraction.
Raising the level of abstraction improves productivity.
That's why we don't do this all the time.
OK, But you, you should know how to do this clearly.
So behavioural HDL, let's talk about behavioural description.
Remember, this was the functional description of the circuit, not necessarily the gate level.
So this enables us to raise the abstraction level, improve productivity, and also enable potential
optimizations that could be done by whoever is mapping the description to an underlying circuit.
With some libraries, there's a compilation step or mapping step that happens using electronic design
automation tools.
Or a very smart person may do that also, right?
OK, there's always this tension between very smart people who can, who know how to optimise code,
and very smart people who think that they can write better compilers, right?
That's true in software, that's true in hardware also.
It exists.
And they always go against each other because very smart people think that they can optimise code
much better than the best compiler that than any other smart, some other smart people can design
and vice versa.
Now this is a good battle.
Actually.
It's interesting to think, OK, so behavioural HDL, this is an example over here.
If this circuit does something, you don't need to figure out what it does.
But essentially this is behavioural, right?
This is the circuit description that we have.
We're not using the gates and, or not NAND, whatever.
We're basically inverting things using this complement behavioural, let's say keyword or letter or
some alphabet, and you can see that.
That A&B&C are inverted and you take the end of it and then there's an OR over here.
So basically we're describing A bitwise circuit over here.
You have a 2-3 inputs and gates that takes a bar B, bar C You're Oring it with another three input
and gates results and Oring it with another three input and gates results.
So you have a three input OR gates in the end.
This is what it looks like, right?
Yeah, 33 input AND gates and you have an OR gates and you have the emergence, which are the these
over here.
So this is a behavioural description that maps nicely to a hardware circuit.
OK, that's not that exciting because it's still very low level, right?
You could also do this.
This is another example you could have.
Now you can see something a little bit different over here.
You get inputs are for example, 4 bits, right?
A&B outputs, you have 5 outputs that are also 4 bits.
So everything is 4 bits over here.
So Y one is A&B.
You can see that this is A OR BA XOR B, this is NAND, this is NOR.
So you can do this also.
And this also maps to a circuit, which is nice.
So you can do bitwise operations behaviourally as you can see, right, you don't need to write the
circuits or NAND and or NOR over here.
Gates.
OK, let's let's see some more interesting things.
So this is a reduction operator.
You have an 8 input bus called A and you have A.
You have one one, sorry, 8 bits bus called A as input and one bit bus or one bit Y are called Y as
output and this is a reduction of A Reduction is essentially you're ending every bit of A and
reducing that value to a single a bit.
This is much easier than to write than this one that I'm not going to read right?
You're ending every single bit.
It's an 88 input and gate basically looks like this.
Now this is a bit more interesting because this saved us a lot of trouble, right?
OK, now let's see more interesting things.
Remember our mocks that we saw earlier?
If you want to actually select, have a 2 input mocks where each bits, so each input is 4 bits.
Those are data inputs.
And then you have a select input and the output is one of those.
Depending on the value of the select input, you can assign it this way.
Basically you're assigning output Y to D1 if select is 1, otherwise D0.
OK, it's an assignment statement.
It's a conditional assignment.
It's also called a ternary operator.
It operates on three inputs SD1D0.
OK, now this is your Max.
It's much better than the Max that we much easier to write than the Max we designed, right?
Because it's really describing the behaviour of the circuit, as opposed to gates that contain the
circuit.
And this is how we can look at it from a schematic level.
This could be implemented in many different ways as we discussed, right?
You could implement this using tri-state buffers, for example, as we have seen in lecture.
You could implement it using NAND gates or gates, NOR gates, anything you want basically, as long as
it's functionally complete and enables implementation.
OK, We can do more complicated conditional assignments.
This is essentially A4 input Max, right?
As opposed to having two data inputs, We have four data inputs, each of them is 4 bits and we're
selecting one of them.
So your select input needs to be two bits as you can see.
And we kind of build it using nested ternary statements, right?
Very similar to what we have seen earlier.
It's you can think of it as building as having a tree of maxes, right?
You have two maxes which are controlled by S0 and their outputs go into another Max which is
controlled by S1, right?
I'm going to show you a picture of that.
There's another way of doing this which is as opposed to a nested statement you do, I guess it's
still nested.
Sorry, another different kind of nested statement.
Instead of checking S1 and then deciding like having checking S0, you kind of distribute S1 and S0
together.
You check S1 and S0 together, right?
2 bit value together.
OK, if S1S0 are one one, then you select D3.
Otherwise if S1S0 are 10 you select D2.
Otherwise if S1S0 are 01, you select D1, otherwise you select D0 and assign it to Y.
OK, so that's a four input marks.
The same thing, except written in two different ways.
Clearly you can also write it this way, right?
If else, if OK, OK, so these are, this is what we've done basically.
This is the first actually both of those describe this one over here.
And this is the structural implementation.
We did not do this.
Basically we did this in that behaviour.
Description.
OK.
Any questions?
Hopefully these are relatively easy and interesting, but yeah, go ahead.
Can you have a race of inputs like now you can specify the zero to 163, you may be like the index
you, yes, you can do that.
You can parameterize things.
We're going to get to that.
Yeah, there are a lot of language features that people have added then.
Yeah, to make it easier.
OK, I'll move on.
So there's also a precedence of operators.
I kind of actually assume that precedence in an earlier thing.
But some operators are the highest precedence.
For example, they apply first, not is the highest precedence.
You apply that and then multiply, divide and modulus comes and then add and subtract and then
shift...
And then eventually you get to ternary operator, which is the lowest precedence.
So for example, here we'd we, yeah, we applied the ternary operator, but then we don't have anything
over here.
So if it if this was for example, some up addition operation addition would get precedence over the
ternary operator or an inversion would get precedence.
So if this was not D3, then that would get precedence over the ternary operator application.
So you would select between not D3 and D2.
OK.
So that's what precedence means in the end.
It's not nice to know all of these.
It's kind of similar to C So it's good to parenthesise in general.
That helps people to think, especially when some of these things are not obvious, usually not as
obvious, but which one has the higher precedent sometimes is not obvious, right?
Yes.
What exactly is the shift operation?
We're going to talk about that.
But essentially you're shifting a value by one bit.
So for example, if your value is 00014 bit value and you're shifting it to the left by one, you're
moving every bit to the left by one.
So the bottom bits goes to the left by 1, the next bit goes to the left by 1, the next bit goes left
by 1, and then the bottom bits gets something inside.
Usually it's a zero OK, So 0001.
If you shifted left by one, it becomes 0010 OK.
If you shifted left by 1 again, it becomes 0100.
OK, Yeah, we're going to see these more when we talk about the ISA.
Yes.
Which index has is the highest bit numerical.
Yeah.
So left, normally left, left, left most bit is the highest, most significant bit, OK.
And the bottom most or right most bit is the lowest.
So in terms of indices, in terms of indices, 0 is the lowest and the higher number is highest.
But again, you can change that also if you actually use the other indexing structure.
It's better to assume that for the purpose of this lecture and whatever, whatever descriptions I
say, 0 is the least significant one, least significant bit.
And as the number, as the number increases, it becomes more and more significant, OK?
So for example, if it's a 32 bit value, bit 31 is the most significant bit.
It has the largest effect.
OK, so how do you express numbers kind of related to what you asked over here.
Essentially this is an 8 bit value that's consists OF00000001.
This is the least significant one.
This is the most significant 1.
You could also express it like this in terms of bytes.
N is the number of bits.
It express how many bits will be used to store the value B is the base over here, can be binary,
hexadecimal, decimal, octal.
** is the number, the value expressed in that particular base.
It can also have invalid and floating values which we have seen.
I'm going to show you more of that_is used to improve readability so that you don't need to figure
out how many zeros are there for example.
So these are some examples over here.
This is a 4 bit value, 1001.
This is a 4 bit value, Decimal 5.
In binary, it's 0101.
That's decimal, right?
Decimal 5.
This is an 8 bit value, 1001.
If it's eight bits and you don't specify the top bits, they're assumed to be 0, right?
This is a 12 bit value, specified in hexadecimal as you can see.
HFA 3FA3 over here.
Again, another 8 bit value.
You could keep doing this for some time, so default is 32 bits.
So if you don't specify the number of bits, you still need to specify the, whether it's binary,
hexadecimal, etcetera.
And you still need to specify some value.
But default is assumed to be 32 bits.
So if you don't want the 32 bit value, you should specify it.
Yes.
OK, OK, floating signals.
We've seen this before.
This is important because you come into these.
This is a signal that's not driven by any circuit, open circuit or floating wire.
We've seen these again, a tri-state buffer.
If you remember, this is how you would input how you describe a tri-state buffer in Verilogue.
Remember, tri-state buffers were very useful.
We're going to see more of those.
It's a four input.
It's a, it's a, it's essentially A4 bit tri-state buffer.
The input is 4 bits A.
There's an enable input like any tri-state buffer and there's an output, 4 bit output.
And essentially the assignment looks like this.
If enable is true, Y is assigned A.
If enable is forced, Y is assigned A4 bit floating signal Z.
OK.
That's how we would implement a tri-state buffer.
And this is recalled from last lectures.
It acts like a switch and we're going to use it to connect CPUs and memories to a shared buses.
And more generally, whenever you want to actually implement a shared wire, it makes sense to
potentially use a tri-state buffer.
You could use other things also, but a tri-state buffer is one thing that we will use.
This is a truth table.
I will let you study on your own, but essentially it's fun to think about this.
If a this is a truth table of AND gate shown as a, let's say 2 dimensional thing, A can take value
01 ZXB, can take value 01 ZX.
And this is the output of the AND gate depending on what values things take.
For example, if any value is 0, the output of the AND gate is definitely 0, right?
But if both values are X, for example, the output of the AND gate is X.
If both values are Z, it's again X because we don't know what the value is.
It's definitely not floating.
It's some value, but we don't know what it is, right?
It's kind of don't care in that sense.
OK, remember the don't cares that we used in the past.
That's also important.
You should you should be able to specify a circuit with don't cares in very long.
So remember the priority circuit.
OK, So what happens with HDL code?
One thing is synthesis, you synthesise the code, the other is simulation.
Now you're going to do both of them in this lecture.
Modern tools map synthesisable HDL code to low level cell libraries.
In the end you will see also in your labs that this will be a net list described in Gates and Wires.
You can actually read it, figure out its format, etcetera.
These tools can perform many optimisations.
So it may not be very easy to read.
It may not be very easy to map the synthesised code back to your Verilog code.
Although if you're if you figure out how to do reverse engineering, you could actually do that.
So if someone is given a net list, you can actually reconstruct what that circuit can potentially
do.
These tools are good, but they're not great.
Let's say they cannot guarantee that a solution is optimal.
Optimal for whenever you throw the word word optimal, you should be careful because optimal for
what?
Right?
Optimal.
These tools are optimal for in general, nothing.
Neither power, energy nor area.
Circuit area.
Because you, if you throw a large circuit to it, it's very hard to actually optimise things to be
and prove that that's the best.
And mainly this is because this is that an expensive problem.
It's anp hard problem actually.
It's very computationally expensive to do.
Placement and routing of the circuits and tools are not good enough here with AI, things are
improving, but there's also a big debate in the community these days actually as to whether the AI
tools are actually better than human design tools because humans have actually improved in this
area a lot.
Neither of them are optimal at this time.
So basically you need to describe your circuit in a nice to synthesise way.
And this is the most common way of digital design these days.
And that's what you will do in your labs basically.
And simulation allows the behaviour of the circuit to be verified without actually manufacturing the
circuit.
So you're going to do a lot of simulation.
And in the end, we're not going to manufacture circuits, we're going to use something called Fpgas.
You're going to program the Fpgas.
That's the beauty of every configurable logic essentially.
And simulators can work on both structural or behavioural HDL.
It's really essential for functional and timing verification as we will see tomorrow.
Let's take a look at this example.
This was the circuit that was interesting synthesising.
You could basically you take this very log, you throw it to a synthesis tool and that's what it
gives you.
It could give you this.
Basically any tool should be able to do that.
And this is the simulation part.
I'll go through this very quickly, but essentially simulation, you will see a lot of this when you
actually simulate your circuit in the labs.
You will have some sort of clock.
Well in this case there's no clock actually.
But you see that you you will be able to see the signals and when you change some of the signals
from zero to 1 circuits, the output of the circuit will change also.
Tomorrow we will cover timing.
So in this simulation there is no timing.
Whenever some value changes, the output also changes, right?
Tomorrow we will see what goes into that timing and it's going to be interesting.
Hopefully I will maybe finish this and then we'll take a break.
But this is actually important.
You're going to see more of This is why it's important in the later part of this lecture.
But, well, maybe I'll read it.
One of the most common mistakes for beginners is to think of HDL as a computer program, rather than
as a shorthand for describing digital hardware.
If you don't know approximately what hardware your HDL should synthesize into, you probably won't
like what you get.
If you care, of course, you might create far more hardware than is necessary, or you might write
code that simulates correctly but cannot be implemented in hardware.
Instead, think of your system in terms of blocks of computational combinational logic registers on
finite state machines.
Sketch these blocks on paper and show how they are connected before you start writing code.
And I definitely agree with this.
It's good to, if you're designing hardware, you should sketch those blocks and then write code.
And we will do that in the labs.
OK, so this is what we've seen so far.
There's more we're going to look at, but first we should take a break.
Then let's be back.
That's 15, let's say 1518 because I want to finish Verilog today and then we'll continue.
OK, hello everyone.
Before you start the lecture, I have a tiny, tiny, tiny, small announcement.
It won't take two minutes.
My name is Frank.
I work at the electrical engineering department.
I know bad people, but we have a project called CIS CHIPS.
The CIS government is giving us some money and they want more IC designs, chips being produced in
Switzerland.
And for that they have teamed up with Matt Van who's running an A service called Tiny Tape Out.
So there is one chip where 205 hundred designs are placed together.
They are manufactured together, they come back, you get the chips, you not only get your chip, you
also get 200 other designs and you can play with it and with your level that you've just covered
here, simple combinational designs, you can actually just put them on a chip, have it manufactured
and come back.
So to explain how this goes, Matt is going to give a webinar March 10th, next Tuesday at six.
It's up there, so you can sign up and say yes, I'm interested, I want to do it.
And if you want to do it, you will get the chip manufactured for free.
You'll also get the board for free.
You have to just sign up and say you're a Swiss resident and everything will work out.
And we want to have as many people coming and doing this.
It's great, it's fun.
And at the moment, let me just a second share the other one.
This is a life, life thing.
@the Moment, we have room for one hundred forty designs @the.
At the moment I have 13, so I need 107 more.
And don't worry if all of you make one, once we reach 140, we will just make it twice as large, so
there is enough room for you to make your chips.
Question.
Yeah.
Just a quick question, will keep the IP of the chip design.
This will be open source.
So you will be making a GitHub action.
So everything, all designs on this chip are open source.
The technology information is open source.
It will be manufactured in Germany by IHP.
The tools used are open source.
So it is completely open.
So it is your IP, your intellectual property is not going to anyone.
Very good question.
Isn't it exciting?
I need to.
I paid for 140.
OK only 13 people join.
I need more or my boss will not be happy.
OK yes I mean some people put their amazing demos.
The good thing is you can actually go to the well you are here.
You can go and check what they did.
I have no idea.
Code name.
Black headed golf.
Well OK, that wasn't a good idea.
Never do live demos.
I lost the page anyway.
I am pretty sure because it's not submitted anyway.
You can go to the tiny table web page and check what everybody else did.
There are people who submitted only an AND gate a multiplexer.
I mean you can do more.
You can do better than that.
You can take one of your exercises.
Some of you have some ideas.
Deadline is March 23rd to submit the design.
It can be done using a web-based schematic thing.
So you can choose the gates connect or you can have a GitHub action using very low code and enter
it.
It is for your level.
This is absolutely doable.
If you are a little bit more interested, you will easily manage to do this.
It's fun and it's for free.
Come on.
OK, thanks a lot.
Thanks.
Thanks, Frank.
You can try it out and see.
Hopefully you'll do better than a single AND gate.
By the way, with the level of knowledge you guys have right now, you can do many things.
So basically we've covered combination Verilog, but we're going to cover sequential, which is going
to be even more interesting.
I think these are, this is what we've covered so far.
You can design structural hierarchy, you can do simple logic, you can do behavioural modelling.
We've looked at multiplexers, we've looked at constants.
There is much more.
Essentially, you can write very long code in many different ways, meaning there are good ways or
easier to read ways and they're harder to read ways.
We're going to look at some examples of this.
If you write at a very low level of abstraction you can get poor readability and but easier
automated optimization potentially because especially for low level tools we can map things easily.
If you write a higher level of abstraction you can get better readability, but it could be more
difficult to optimise things in a better way.
There could be a large search space because going from a very abstract X abstract description to a
very low level implementation may require a huge source space for the tools, even for tools that
know a lot, meaning that I've seen a lot of these designs trained with AI for example.
So it's good to think about this.
So let's take a look at something as simple as comparing 2 numbers.
You can define your own gates as new modules.
We're going to do an equality checker checker, which you have seen.
Essentially, we're going to look at different ways of implementing A4 bit compared.
So we're going to use, for example, 2 input X nor gates.
This is an X nor gates written in behavioural Verilog AX or B.
And then this is the not of that, right?
And you assign variable Z to that.
And this is a true input and gates A&B.
You've seen that.
Again, this is behavioural.
It's not really the gate primitive that Verilog uses.
But remember a four bit comparator.
This is what our 4 bit comparator was a couple of lectures ago.
Constructed from 42 input X NOR gates and 1/4 input NAND.
Which could 1A14 input and gate, which could be a three of three two input and gates also, right?
And this is our gate level implementation, which looks pretty ugly, right?
So essentially I've defined my XNOR inputs ABZ and my and inputs ABZ.
Essentially this is a direct implementation of this, except this four input and gate doesn't exist
for us.
It's 232 input and gates.
So you have 4 xnores and then three ants.
You get bored at some point and you name them in different ways as you can see.
OK, so clearly this is not readable, I would say.
I mean it's readable, but it takes some time.
So you can change things.
You can do these assignments.
So you still keep the xnores over here and then do the ends like this.
Behavioural.
This is behavioural now, right?
I mean, the previous thing was also behavioural, but modules, you, you connected modules, you got
rid of modules over here that are not necessarily you turn them into ends like this.
And you can also do this, there's a for input behavioural and statement bitwise AND which could be
implemented as a for input and gate.
So this sounds much better now ignores.
Let's try to get rid of them also.
So one thing you could do is instead of having inputs like this, you could have 4 bits inputs and
four bit output wire and you can do this.
This is good.
You simplified some things, but this is actually a much better X N.O.R.E.
Clearly 4 bit X N.O.R.E, right?
And this is actually a much better way of doing comparison of the two bit numbers.
So you can see that you could have done things like this.
Equal is assigned to the output of this ternary equation.
And the output ternary equation outputs one if a is equal to B, otherwise it outputs 0, right?
That's what it is.
So which one do you guys prefer?
This one or this one?
Yes.
What would be the output of this like A equal to B expression?
That's a good question, basically, I think.
So yes, you should be able to do that.
But again, try compiling and check it.
I'm not a big believer in memorizing syntax, so yeah, OK.
And this is where an AI tool can help a lot, you know, get rid of the memorisation aspect that
humans don't need to really deal with.
Although there's some values of that also if you ask me.
But OK, OK, very good.
That's a very good question.
Basically you can simplify it even further perhaps.
OK, so essentially writing more reusable very long code is nicer, but this is not reusable enough.
For example, what if you want to compare an 8 bit numbers, right?
This is hard wired to 4 bit numbers.
So that's why we have parameterised modules.
You don't want to write code for each case.
And in parameterised modules you can define module parameters.
So this is for example A2 input Max.
The width of each of the inputs can be specified with the width parameter.
The default value is 8.
So by default if you don't specify the parameter width you get an 8 bit to input Max.
But this could be any width to input Max.
OK, when instantiating the module you just need to specify the width.
So this is our module when you instantiate it.
This is for example the 8 bits.
So inputs are 8 bits D0 and D1 and alt are 8 bits here, because we didn't specify a value here, we
specify 12 like.
This is the syntax as you can see, and the inputs and outputs are 12 bits in this case, except for
select of course rate.
So this is another way of doing it.
This is a more verbose version where you actually specify the width, right?
OK, so they're both the same thing.
And also you specify the connections over here.
OK, so timing, it's possible to also define timing relations in Verilogue, but this is not what
timing you will get when you actually implement when when someone actually maps the code to a
circuit.
This is more for a simulation.
Essentially you can put timing.
These cannot be synthesised because they may not be possible to actually observe that timing.
They're used for modelling delays.
When you simulate things.
For example, you can specify a time scale and you can basically assign and this assignment in
simulation.
When you simulate this thing, you get an inverted output Z1 after 5 nanoseconds after the beginning
of the simulation and you get an you get.
A assigned to Z2 after 9 nanoseconds.
OK, this is good for a simulation.
Now you will do that when you simulate things for for real timing, we're going to see tomorrow, Yes.
logic gate or two logic gates?
Well, in this in this particular case, there is no logic depth, right?
You're basically specifying it functionally this morning a relation to the labs in relation to the
labs.
So is it specific to a lab question then ask it within the context of the labs because I don't know
exactly the context of the question.
OK, but for this particular case, when you instantiate an extort gate, there is no concept of logic
depth, right?
You're just describing things unless you have a structural extort gate where you actually show the
built it using Ands and Nands.
OK.
But the lab questions I think folks here would be able to answer, OK, there's more on the timing
soon and more on the simulation soon, but we're going to see the timing tomorrow.
We're going to go actually a lot deeper in the time.
So there are a bunch of good practices that I would recommend develop and use a good consistent
naming style, essentially MSP to LSP ordering for buses use this one that I assumed and one of you
asked questions about as opposed to this one.
Basically 0 should be least significant bits.
Larger numbers should specify more powerful or more significant bits.
Define one module per file in general, and use a file name that matches the module name.
Always keep in mind that Verilog describes hardware.
That's why I read the quote from your book.
OK, so this is what we've done so far, combinational logic.
And let's talk about sequential logic because sequential logic things become interesting as we have
seen last time, right?
Because you need to describe flip flops, for example, or latches.
And these are two different sequential constructs as we have seen.
And you remember sequential is combinational plus memory.
So it's always more complex than just combinational.
Essentially we need to, we want to define blocks that have memory.
These are flip flops, latches and build finite state machines out of them.
So we need the notion of a clock and sequential logic.
State transition is triggered by a clock signal in synchronous design, as we have discussed, latches
are sensitive to the level of that signal.
Flip flops are sensitive to the transitioning, meaning the edge of the signal, like going from zero
to 1, rising edge of the clock for example as we have discussed, or falling edge of the clock.
Unfortunately, what we've seen so far are not sufficient to express the sequential logic to describe
it.
We need new constructs and Verilog introduces a couple of contracts.
Always pause edge and neg edge.
You can guess what those are always a bit different, so we'll see Always.
So always looks like this.
This is a block that you can write.
Always add some sensitivity list of signals you execute some statement.
This means that whenever the event in the sensitivity list occurs, the statement is executed.
OK, so recall the D flip flop.
We're going to implement the D flip flop in very log and it's going to be very easy to implement.
But remember what we wanted was state change on clock edge and we wanted the data output of the flip
flop available for the full clock cycle.
And you remember the clock cycle is from 1 rising edge of the clock to the other rising edge of the
clock.
And this is how we designed the D flip flop to from 2D latches.
And this is the module that hides the details of the underlying implementation.
As you can see, the key is that the rising edge of the clock clock going from zero to 1 Q should get
assigned D At all other times, Q should be unchanged.
So.
This is how we implemented the state register.
We're going to implement more of these, but let's first build this D flip flop.
And it's like this in Verilog.
So you can see that Verilog makes it simple.
So this is flop, Let's called flop input.
You have a clock input, you have a four bit D input, it's a four bit D flip flop, and you have a
four bit Q output.
There's something special called Reg over here.
We're going to talk about that later.
You need to declare it as Reg because it's stateful and this is the description behavioural, always
at the positive edge of clock, meaning clock signal goes from zero to 1, Q gets D and there's some
special symbol over here.
It's A.
It's essentially a non blocking assignment as we will discuss later.
We're going to separate it from the blocking assignments.
OK, this is your description of flip flop in Verilogs.
Nice friendly way.
You may not find it friendly at this point, but it's going to become more and more friendly as you
do things, just like in any language.
This sounds good right?
This is my flip flop.
I don't need to deal with a gate level description.
This is how I describe.
Type AD flip flop because this is going to be a huge basic, basic building block of any finite state
machine that you built.
And this is the power of a hardware description language.
It lets you do these things easily.
OK, so a pause edge defines a rising edge.
Transition from zero to one statement is executed when the clock signal rises.
That's what always means always at the positive edge of clock.
Do this.
The value of D is copied to Q OK input is.
The output is Q OK.
So a sign statement is not used within an always block.
That's forbidden.
Essentially, you'll get a compiler, hopefully with a good compiler.
And this odd thing that kind of looks like less than or equal to or poor man's less than or equal to
describes a non blocking assignment, right?
And we will see the difference between blocking non blocking assignment soon.
This is assigned variables need to be declared as Reg.
The name Reg is kind of unfortunate.
It doesn't necessarily mean that the values are registered.
It could be, but it doesn't have to be.
It's just the syntax that someone decided.
We will see examples of this later also, but let me introduce the notion of reset also.
We didn't do this when we talked about flip flop, but it's going to be important when you design
finite state machines.
As we discussed in the last lecture, you should start from a known state.
Any finite state machine should have a state that you reset the machine into.
That's your beginning state, basically start state.
And there are two ways of doing research.
We're going to use synchronous reset a lot in this course, but there's also asynchronous reset.
It's good to know.
Essentially you reset the signals you you use the these reset signals to initialise flip flops or
state the hardware to a known state.
Usually this happens at system start up on power up.
Some of you had questions actually about resetting but I didn't cover it in class.
Now we're this is the time to cover it.
So asynchronous reset means that the reset signals sampled independently of the clock, just like
anything asynchronous.
Actually reset gets the highest priority in this case.
And as we will see tomorrow, this is sensitive to a lot of issues like glitches, meta stability.
You will learn more about these tomorrow.
We talked about meta stability when we introduced the cross coupled NAND gates.
Cross coupled NAND gates, right?
You both SNR should not be equal to 1 at the same time.
We discussed this.
We're going to talk about that more synchronous reset, which we're going to use a lot, is reset
signal sampled with respect to clock over here.
And in this case, the reset signal should be active long enough to get sampled at the clock edge,
because at the positive edge of the clock, for example, if reset is one or zero, depending on how
you think about reset, usually people think of reset being 0 as resetting things.
You basically reset the value to zero.
OK, So this results in a completely synchronous sequential circuit.
Now we're going to implement the flip flops with reset and we've seen asynchronous versus
synchronous state changes.
This slide that I copied and pasted, it's essentially asynchronous versus synchronous reset goes
into the heart of design as asynchronous versus synchronous.
These are some a signal could be asynchronous versus synchronous be sampled.
OK, so this is an example of a Deflip flop with asynchronous reset.
Let's take a look at what's going on over here.
Somebody threw this code at you.
There are two inputs, clock and reset.
There there's another 4-4 bit data input and there's a Reg output 4 bits always at the positive edge
of clock and negative edge of reset.
This code is executed.
That's what this means essentially.
Yeah, 2 events triggers the execution of this always block.
There's a begin and end as you can see.
We added that for easy ease of reading.
Rising edge of clock or falling edge of reset.
When the reset goes down and if the reset is signal IS0Q gets assigned, 0Q gets zero.
That means in this case A0 reset signal means that you should reset the output the flip flop,
otherwise Q gets D So basically we added this if reset 0 over here to be reset able.
So we use begin and end over here to improve readability.
In this example it was not necessary because if an else is complete, actually there's no other
statement but begin and end are always good.
So this basically sets you first check reset if reset IS0Q is set to 0 otherwise you check Q gets D.
So this is an asynchronous reset, as the reset can happen independently of the clock.
Basically, you're executing the statement when reset goes from 1 to 0 OK.
On the negative edge of the reset signal.
Hopefully this is clear, we're just going through some code to understand it.
If there is no reset, meaning assume that reset never goes to the negative edge, then this this
simplifies to always that positive edge of clock Q gets D right?
If reset never goes to 0 or negative edge, that's what happens.
OK, so this is that was asynchronous reset a flip flop AD flip flop with synchronous reset looks
like this essentially, I'll I'll go through this.
So here, here we got rid of the negative edge reset from the always block because we don't want
anything else triggering state change.
OK, state change is triggered, meaning the statement is executed only at the positive edge of clock.
And if reset happens to be 0 at that point, Q gets 0, otherwise Q gets D You either sample the reset
signal or the input D signal at the positive edge of clock.
OK, for you to be able to reset the flip flop, you'd better have the reset 0 at a positive edge of
clock when you're beginning, let's say to reset your machine for example, right?
Yes.
Why did you have one?
You could do it also potentially, but I guess the question is assignment.
You cannot do multiple assignments, right?
Because you're assigning a single variable.
If you have multiple always blocks, it's not, it's not modelling the same hardware, right?
If you have two different always blocks.
So how are you going to assign Q in this case?
In one case, you're going to assign Q in one way, in other case, you're going to assign Q in some
other way, Right.
OK, think about it.
We'll get to that.
Actually, you cannot assign Q in two different always blocks, same output.
You can think of it that way.
Yeah.
Basically reset happens only when the clock rises.
It's a synchronous reset.
The process is sensitive.
The process meaning the always block is sensitive only to the positive edge of clock.
OK.
There are also some things like an enabled flip flop.
There's an enabled signal, let's go, right, right.
Enable, for example, it's just called enable.
That's another signal that you can input.
This is AD flip flop with enable and reset.
It happens to be asynchronous reset over here, always at the positive edge of clock and the negative
reset.
If reset IS0Q gets 0.
Otherwise, only if enable is true, Q gets D OK, so that's a right enable signal for example, right?
We've seen the right enable, so you can build a right enabled memory with this.
OK, Note that the enable signal is not in the sensitivity list over here because it's a synchronous
signal, OK, Q gets D only when clock is rising and enable is one.
OK, so that was flip flop.
Now let's build a latch because in some cases you may want a latch, right?
You're not using the latch for as a state register, but it may be useful in your design.
This is our latch.
You should be able to read it right now and think that it's a latch.
Basically, I don't have the positive edge of clock.
My input sensitivity list is clock and D always when clock and D, either of them changes.
If clock it's true, meaning clock is high, Q gets assigned D This was exactly the problem with latch
that we tried to solve.
But this means that this is a good description of the latch, right?
Basically, whenever the clock is high, Q should get assigned D That's the definition of a latch,
right?
Otherwise, Q doesn't get assigned anything, which is it retains the old value.
OK, and this is exactly doing that.
That could happen when D changes or when clock changes.
OK, so this is the sensitive list.
When D changes, if the clock IS0Q doesn't get assigned anything, which means it keeps its old value.
But when D changes, if clock is 1, Q gets assigned the new value of D OK, that's a latch.
OK, sounds good, hopefully.
So this is the summary we've seen.
This is going to get a little bit more interesting and maybe a little bit more complicated.
But basically if you want sequential statements, you should do them in an always block.
The sequential block is triggered with a change in the sensitivity list.
Basically you can put anything in the sensitivity list.
Whenever that signal changes, that statement is executed.
That always.
Block is executed.
Signals assigned within always must be declared as Reg.
They're not necessarily registers, they're more stateful elements that are assigned.
And we use this less than or equal to our poor man's less than or equal to 4 non blocking
assignments and do not use assign within the always block.
OK, so let's take a look at these always blocks a little bit more.
For example, this is one circuit that you can look at.
You can have as many always blocks as needed.
So for example, you're assigning special to D at the positive edge of clock and then inverting
special doing normal, let's say.
And then you're assigning also at the positive edge of clock normal to Q.
These are two different flip flops arrays that we have.
Hopefully you can think of that.
OK, assignment to same signal are different.
Always blocks is not allowed because that doesn't describe hardware, right?
You could potentially get into a situation where these actually look at the completely exclusive
cases of assignment, but it's it becomes a mess to program describe hardware that way.
So think of this as hardware as opposed to assigned of a variable, right?
If it's hardware, then all of the operations that affect a signal should happen concurrently, right?
It shouldn't happen with two always blocks.
It should happen at the same time yes.
So the the delay of actually going to the wire and inverting it and then setting it again is
comfortable.
Yeah, but the, but remember there are two flip flops over here, right?
One is at the positive edge of clock special gets D and then you sample this one, right?
So it actually takes 2 clock.
We're going to get to that.
That's correct.
Yes, that's correct.
We're going to get to that though.
Yeah, I'm going to get to the like assignment statements later on.
No, no.
How how long it takes, but you're right.
OK, but very good.
Yes.
Does this get compiled to like some transistor level implementation?
It could get compiled, yeah.
It's it's you can compile this perfectly using some compilation flow, yes.
But so maybe, maybe I can describe what you said over here.
Right at the positive edge of clock, this D special gets assigned D, right?
And propagation of this takes some time.
We'll get to that.
Let me get to it later, OK?
But before there's some other things that we should get out of the way, right?
Like you may actually have the question, does it always lock remember things, right?
Why does it remember things?
Because it's sequential, right?
So this statement over here with the always describes what happens to signal Q.
So when clock rises, D gets copied into Q, right?
Or Q gets D when the clock is not rising, what happens, right?
It basically keeps the old value, right?
The value of Q is preserved, remembered.
So it implicitly preserves the value even though we don't explicitly say anything about Q when it
when there's no positive edge of clock, right?
That's why this remembers.
Now it's good to think that it doesn't always remember.
An always block doesn't always specify A sequential circuit, right?
Let's take a look at this example over here.
You have an always block that gets triggered with invalid and data.
So whenever invalid or data changes, this underlying block gets executed.
If an else statement.
If invalid is true, result gets the converted a complemented value of data, otherwise result gets
data.
OK, so this is actually a combinational circuit.
Essentially when invalid is 1, result is data bar, when invalid is not one, result is data, right?
That's combinational, right?
The way I described it, meaning what does combinational mean?
Result is assigned a value whenever an input value changes.
And in all cases of the FNLS block.
OK, so there's nothing that's remembered over here.
Think about it.
OK, now N always block defines.
This makes it a little bit more powerful, but also maybe a little bit harder to think right.
But I think once you keep doing things, you'll learn more.
N always block defines combination logic.
If all outputs are always continuously updated, what does this mean?
All right hand signals are in the sensitivity list, which was the case over here.
Basically these are the inputs in invalid and data.
Whenever invalid and data changes, all outputs.
Results.
The result is the only output gets updated, right?
So basically all right hand signals inputs are in the sensitivity list.
You can use always at for short, at at star for short, and all left hand signals get assigned in
every possible condition of if and else or case blocks.
We'll see the case blocks in a little bit.
Meaning it also becomes easy to make mistakes and unintentionally describe memorising elements.
So if you want to use always blocks to actually do combinational logic, you may make mistakes, you
may get warnings or may not get warnings, but it's good to check your warning messages, right?
You may get a latch basically sometimes, OK, but always blocks actually allow powerful combinational
logic statements using if else cases.
So let's take a look at this exercise, sequential versus combinational.
Is this sequential or combinational?
Does this block remember?
Yeah, 50% chance.
So who says this is sequential?
OK, who says this is combinational?
Who says I have no idea, which is fine, OK, OK, we're going to go through this.
So this is sequential.
So people who said sequential is right essentially.
So let's take a look at when.
So what is the combinational logic?
Combinational logic means that all outputs are updated whenever inputs are changed, right?
So for this to be sequential under some changes of the inputs, outputs should not change, right?
So if you look over here, the sensitive list contains everything on the right hand side, meaning
anything changes.
This is executed fine.
Output A is updated always, which means that output A is really combinational, right?
But output B doesn't get updated unless enable is true, right?
Meaning if enable is not true, output B preserves its previous value regardless of whatever changed.
Makes sense.
That's why this is sequential.
Hopefully that's clear.
OK, let's do another one.
Is this combinational or sequential?
There's no reason, but this is actually correct.
But this, this I'm going to handle that issue later on.
This is actually a there's actually a good reason.
Yes, you'll see that too.
There's a non blocking assignment essential, but we'll see that soon.
Let's not confuse that right now.
Assume that.
OK, don't assume that, but assume that this is correct code.
OK, that's a very good observation.
OK, what about the what about what about this one over here?
Is this combinational or sequential?
Yes, combinational, yes.
The problem is this is not in the sensitivity list, meaning if data changes but enable doesn't
change, you don't trigger this block.
OK, so this is actually sequential also.
Yeah, it's very tricky as you can see, right, especially when you're starting.
But this is tricky regardless.
So yeah, you guys have very good questions.
So we're going to get to that non blocking versus blocking issue soon.
So there's always block is not always practical or nice.
This is one example of this.
Both of these, for example, describe the same multiplexer.
This was a multiplexer that we designed, right?
Always block is one way of implementing the multiplexer.
But this is much nicer as you can see, right?
Much cleaner.
Although this is not unreasonable either, right?
But it's more work.
OK, so for case statements, always blockers could be nice.
This comes in handy.
For example, always at any right hand input change, you check the data and you assign segments to
some of the input data values.
Part of the part of the input data values, right?
If if the sorry, you say you assign segments to a particular values depending on the input value of
the data, right?
So it's easy to do this.
So you can do this conditional assignment based on the input value of the data.
OK, so essentially this is powerful.
You can use if and else and you can use if and else only in the always blocks.
It's combinational only.
If all of the registers within the always block are always assigned to a signal and you can use a
default case with case statements like here, by default segments is assigned to some number over
here.
And you can use the case X statement to be able to check for don't cares, which I haven't shown you,
but you can find that.
Now let's go to that question that you asked earlier, like what What about this poor man's less than
or equal to signal versus equal to signal?
What's the difference?
The Senator nuance, but it exists.
So here it becomes interesting, especially when you have two things assigned over here and they may
or may not depend on each other.
So this is non blocking over here.
That's the poor man's signal.
That's what non blocking means.
Non blocking means that all assignments are made at the end of the block.
Basically you don't sequentially execute the block.
All assignments are made at the end of the block.
For example, here, or in other words, all assignments are made in parallel.
Process flow is not blocked.
So if you look over here, A gets the value of one right.
The question is should B get the value of 1 or should B get the previous value of A?
In this particular case because it's non blocking, all assignments are executed concurrently.
B gets the previous value of A which we don't know.
So here I can guarantee you that at the end of the execution of the always block, A is 1 BI.
Don't know it was the previous value of A.
OK, OK, now let's take a look at the blocking version of this.
Blocking version is more sequential.
The assignments are done 1 by 1.
For example, in this particular case, A is assigned 1 and B gets that new value of A OK, so B at the
end of the statement, both A&B are one.
Each assignment is made immediately OK and the process waits until the 1st assignment is complete,
meaning it blocks.
That's why it's blocking.
So this assignment is blocking, it completes and then the next assignment is done over here.
OK, yes, but does this actually change the synthesis?
I mean OK in this case it's a it will change the synthesis, right?
But does it actually create some sequential logic thing in Gates?
Yeah, that's a good question.
Basically, you need to think about that.
Yes, yes, certainly it, it will need to do whatever it takes to implement the semantics, right?
That's also possible depending on depending on what changes, right?
In this particular case, we don't have an always at B, so there's some remembrance going on, right?
So if you want to synthesise, you need to go through all of those cases.
But these are very good questions.
Yes, it also sets a in this block.
It can trigger the always block in an.
You can, you can think of it that way.
Yes, exactly.
At some point, this block gets triggered whenever a changes, right?
So you're right, it's good to think about it.
Eventually the work circuit settles.
OK, we're I'm going to say show you an example of this if you have time, otherwise tomorrow.
OK, so these are very good questions.
You guys are thinking what's going on basically in the hardware.
OK, so this is the second one is clearly similar to similar sequential programs, right?
In sequential programs, this is what happens.
You don't have this in sequential programs on the left, but this is very useful for defining, let's
say what happens in a clock cycle, right?
Because in in remember in the finite state machine you have some state registers, there could be
many of them, A&B, both of them.
And then you use those input values and the combination logic executes and only at the end of the
clock cycle you get A&B assigned.
So the first one is more like that sequential logic, the second one is more like the sequential
program that you design.
OK, why do you use non blocking or blocking statements?
Essentially non blocking statements allow operating on old values.
As I said, they enable easy sequential logic descriptions.
Blocking statements allow a sequence of operations, allow operating on immediately updated values.
It's more like a software programming language, right?
This doesn't mean it's combinational.
So that's a different question you kind of asked earlier.
You still need to think about whether it's sequential or combinational, but more like a software
programming language.
If the sensitivity list is correct, a block with non blocking statements will eventually evaluate to
the same result as the same block with blocking statements.
You may need to think about what I just said.
This may require additional iterations like you asked earlier.
Let's take a look at this for example.
So this is this is our blocking assignments.
This is actually your carry generation circuitry for for a carry look ahead adder.
You haven't seen carrier look ahead, but I recommend that you take a look at it.
You don't need to, but this is a carrier generation circuitry.
You have PGS and then C out and these are some operations as you can see and this is at over here
meaning on all, whenever any of the things on the right hand changes, you trigger this block,
right?
So initially assume that P everything is 0.
If a changes to 1, all values are updated in order, right?
Because this is blocking.
This becomes one, this becomes 0, this becomes one, this becomes zero.
OK, let's take a look at the same thing.
Exact same thing with an unblocking assignment sensitivity list.
Whatever on the right hand list changes, you trigger this.
So initially everything is 0 PGSC out.
They're all zeros now.
If a changes to 1, all assignments happen concurrently.
This changes to one.
This is 0.
Still.
Also, right now, because P changed, P changed.
This statement gets executed again right after the first iteration.
P has changed to 1 as well.
Since there's a change in P, the process triggers again.
This time S is calculated with P1.
So this becomes one, this becomes 0, this becomes one, this becomes zero at the end.
OK, so that's that's essentially how this works.
Let me finish this and then we're going to part.
Essentially always use always a positive edge of clock and non blocking assignments.
Meaning poor man's less than or equal to tomorrow's synchronous sequential logic.
That's beautiful.
That's our non blocking thing.
But use continuous assignments to model simple combinational logic.
There's a bit more use always and star everything in the right hand side of the in the sensitivity
list and blocking assignments to model more complicated combinational logic.
So if you use other things, things become dangerous basically.
But if you use star and blocking assignments, then you're doing combination logic, OK?
You cannot make assignments to the same signal in more than one always block or in a continuous
assignment.
So this is not allowed.
This was your question earlier because it doesn't describe hardware nicely.
Let's say even though you may have a correct thing in your mind, it may still not work.
It's not allowed basically because you may make a lot of mistakes.
It's also not allowed.
OK.
So we're going to pick up here tomorrow and continue with timing and verification.